Guide to the Felix Adler Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series II: Classified Papers
  - Subseries II.3 Single Lectures and Addresses by Dr. Adler (500)
    - 523 Lectures
      - Lecture Mss. in Dr. Adler's Handwriting, 1876-1880
        - The Educated Class in its Relation to Religion (Box 81, Folder 34.1)
        - Liberal Christianity (Box 81, Folder 35)
        - Our Fourth Anniversary (Box 81, Folder 36)
        - The Highest Good (Box 81, Folder 37)
        - The Founding of Christianity (Box 81, Folder 38)
        - A Great Reformation (Box 81, Folder 39)
        - The New Ideal (Box 81, Folder 40)
        - The Origin of Religion (3 lectures) (Box 81, Folder 41)
        - Benedict Spinoza (Box 81, Folder 42)
        - The Office of the Priest (Box 81, Folder 43)
        - The Modern Priest (Box 81, Folder 44)
        - Religion and Ethics (Box 81, Folder 45)
        - Dreams and Ideals (Box 81, Folder 46)
        - Education and Liberty (Box 81, Folder 47)
        - The Form of Religion (Box 81, Folder 47.1)
        - Liberal Judaism (Box 81, Folder 48)
        - Liberal Christianity (Box 81, Folder 49)
        - The Education of Women to Freedom (Box 81, Folder 50)
        - Our Consolations (Box 81, Folder 51)
        - The Old and the New (Box 81, Folder 51.1)
        - First Anniversary Address (Box 81, Folder 52)
        - The Religion of Humanity (Box 81, Folder 53)
        - The Work of the Society (Box 81, Folder 54)
        - The Religion of Humanity (Box 81, Folder 55)
        - The Ethical School (Box 81, Folder 56)
        - The Bible as an Instrument of Ethical Culture (Box 81, Folder 57)
        - The Ethical School (Box 81, Folder 58)
        - Festivals (Box 81, Folder 59)
        - The One Thing Needful (Box 81, Folder 60)
        - The Ethics of Luxury (Box 81, Folder 61)
        - The Ethics of the Social Question (3 lectures) (Box 81, Folder 62)
        - Religion and Social Reform (Box 81, Folder 63)
        - The Atonement (3 lectures) (Box 81, Folder 64)
        - Fact and Fiction in Religion (Box 81, Folder 65)
        - Education and Liberty (2 lectures) (Box 81, Folder 66)
        - The Teachers of Religion (Box 81, Folder 67)
        - Woman’s Mission (Box 81, Folder 68)
        - Judaism, Christianity, and Humanity (Box 81, Folder 69)
        - Second Anniversary Address (Box 81, Folder 70)
        - The Cost of Emancipation (Box 81, Folder 71)
        - The New Departure (Box 81, Folder 72)
        - Our Leader (Box 81, Folder 73)
        - Have We Still A Religion? (Box 81, Folder 74)
        - Conscience (Box 81, Folder 75)
        - The Problem of Human Happiness (Box 81, Folder 76)
        - The Conduct of Life (3 lectures) (Box 81, Folder 77)
        - Race and Religion (Box 81, Folder 78)
        - A Chosen People (Box 81, Folder 79)
        - What to Preserve in Religion (Box 81, Folder 80)
        - Social Conservation (Great Changes) (Box 81, Folder 81)
  - Subseries II.4. Lecture Series by Dr. Adler (600); Berlin Lectures (600); Miscellaneous Manuscripts
    The Classification of the 600s is as follows:
    600 Plymouth Lectures
    601 Washington School of Ethics
    602 Oxford Lectures on Culture
    603 Lowell Institute Lecture
    604 Berlin Lectures and German Materials
    Miscellaneous Manuscripts:
    605 Miscellaneous Addresses, Lectures and Notes
    606 Miscellaneous Notes with Uniform Titles
    607 Extracts from Adler's Writings
    608 Miscellaneous Manuscripts (untitled; some incomplete)
    609 Miscellaneous Manuscripts by Others
    - 600-604 Lecture Series
      - 600 Plymouth Lectures, 1891-1895
        - Opening Exercises (Box 82, Folder 1)
        - Sketch of First Lecture (Box 82, Folder 1)
        - The Struggle of the Plebeians with the Patricians (Box 82, Folder 1)
        - The Rise of Greek Democracy (Box 82, Folder 1)
        - The Boundaries of Ethics in Economic Science: Lecture and Notes to second lecture (Box 82, Folder 2)
        - Strikes and Boycotts: Lecture and draft of third lecture, 1897 July 15 (Box 82, Folder 3)
        - Arbitration, etc.: Notes, Draft and fourth lecture, 1895 July 18 (Box 82, Folder 4)
        - Influence of Industrial and Social Conditions on the Family: Fifth Lecture, 1895 July 23 (Box 82, Folder 5)
        - Spiritual Regeneration as a means of Industrial Progress; Socialism (Box 82, Folder 6)
        - The Abolition of Slavery (Box 82, Folder 7)
        - Individualism; The Organization of Industries (Box 82, Folder 8)
        - Criticism of Socialism The Ethics of Remuneration (Box 82, Folder 9)
        - Organic Education (Box 82, Folder 10)
        - The Economic Principle The Relations of the State to Economic Progress (Box 82, Folder 11)
        - The Church and the Labor Question (Box 82, Folder 12)
        - Carlyle’s Doctrine of Work (Box 82, Folder 13)
        - Notes
          - On the Craft Guilds (Box 82, Folder 14)
          - The Struggle for Existence (Box 82, Folder 14)
          - What Are Economic Goods? (Box 82, Folder 14)
          - The Relation of the State to Industrial Action (Box 82, Folder 14)
      - 601 Washington School of Ethics
        - Introductory
          - Sketch of the Opening Address (Box 82, Folder 1)
          - Branches of Study in a Department of Ethics (Box 82, Folder 1)
          - The School of Ethics (Box 82, Folder 1)
          - Summary of Lectures by Stimson, Adams, King, Nash, etc. (Box 82, Folder 1)
          - Labor Conference (Box 82, Folder 1)
          - Injunction and Organized Labor (Box 82, Folder 1)
          - The School System (Box 82, Folder 1)
          - Fouilleé’s “Education from the National Standpoint" (Box 82, Folder 1)
        - Education; Critique of Aims and Methods (Box 82, Folder 2)
        - The Ethical Passion (Box 82, Folder 3)
        - Darwin's Theory of Conscience (Box 82, Folder 4)
        - Moral Education Proper (Box 82, Folder 5)
      - 602 Oxford Lectures on Culture
        - First Lecture (Box 82, Folder 1)
        - Second Lecture (Box 82, Folder 2)
        - Third Lecture (Box 82, Folder 3)
        - Fourth Lecture (Box 82, Folder 4)
      - 603 Lowell Institute Lectures
        - Ethics of Marriage (Box 83, Folder 1)
        - Spiritual Meaning of Marriage (Box 83, Folder 2)
        - Ideal of Marriage (Box 83, Folder 3)
        - [Individual and Social Aspects of Marriage] (Box 83, Folder 4)
        - [Women in America] (Box 83, Folder 5)
        - [Women in History] (Box 83, Folder 6)
      - 604 Berlin Lectures and German Materials
        - Felix Adler's Father [Autobiography of Samuel Adler] t.ms. (Box 83, Folder 1)
        - Trendalburg--Pedagogik II (Box 83, Folder 2)
        - Steinthal-- Psychologie (Box 83, Folder 2)
        - Einleitung in die Psychologie (Box 83, Folder 2)
        - Geiger-- Einleitung in die Biblischen Schriften (Box 83, Folder 2)
        - Bonitz-- Geschichte der Griechen Philosophie (Box 83, Folder 2)
        - Billman-- Einleitung in das Alta Testament (Box 83, Folder 2)
        - Petermann—Samaritanische Grammatik Deuteronomium (Box 83, Folder 3)
        - Aeussere Einleitung (Box 83, Folder 3)
        - Geiger—Geschichte der Indischen Stämme Targum (Box 83, Folder 3)
        - Duehring-- Geschichte der Philosophie (Box 83, Folder 3)
        - Geiger-- Einleitung in die Biblischen Schriften (Box 83, Folder 3)
        - Roediger—Erklarungen zur Genesis (Box 83, Folder 3)
        - Steinschneider-- Halachische Literatur (Box 83, Folder 3)
        - Steinthal-- Encyclopaedia und Methologie der Philologie (Box 83, Folder 3)
        - German Notes (Box 83, Folder 3)
        - Die Kant'sche Deduction des Grundsatzes der Causalitaet (Box 83, Folder 4)
        - Erkenntnis Theorie (Wundt’s Logic) (Box 83, Folder 4)
        - Vienna Addresses; Lecture in Berlin on the Ethical Society, 1892 (Box 83, Folder 5)
        - Berlin Lectures Numbered 1-5, 1906 (Box 83, Folder 6)
        - Berlin Lectures Numbered 6-10, 1908 (Box 83, Folder 7)
        - Berlin Lectures Numbered 11-16, 1908 (Box 83, Folder 8)
        - Berlin Lectures Numbered 17-23, 1908 (Box 83, Folder 9)
        - Berlin Lectures, 1909 January-February (Box 84, Folder 10)
        - Berlin Notes, 1909 February (Box 84, Folder 11)
        - Berlin Lectures: Notes, 1908-1909 (Box 84, Folder 12)
        - German Notes: DeTocqueville, Hamlet, Ethical Society (Box 84, Folder 13)
        - Berlin Lectures on Lincoln (German and English) (Box 84, Folder 14)
        - Berlin Lectures: Miscellaneous Notes for German Lectures, 1908-1909 (Box 84, Folder 15)
          (DeTocqueville; Millon Liberty; William V. Humboldt; Stephen on Liberty Equality, Fraternity; Sir James Stephen; John C. Calhoun -- Government)
        - Manuscripts and Notes in German, circa 1870-1900 (Box 84, Folder 16)
          (Untitled and Incomplete)
        - Manuscripts and Notes in German, circa 1870-1879 (Box 84, Folder 17)
          (Untitled and Incomplete; See Also: No. 514-2 Across the Sea (Berlin) )
    - 605-609 Miscellaneous Manuscripts
      - 605 Miscellaneous Addresses, Lectures, and Notes
        - Titles, A-G (Box 85, Folder 1)
        - Titles, H-Z (Box 85, Folder 2)
        - Untitled, by date (Box 85, Folder 3a)
        - Untitled, undated (Box 85, Folder 3b)
      - 606 Miscellaneous Notes with Uniform Titles
        - Memoranda: Specific Topics, A-Z (Box 86, Folder 1a)
        - Memoranda: General Topics, unarranged (Box 86, Folder 1b)
        - Obiter Dicta (Box 86, Folder 2)
      - 607 Extracts from Adler’s Writings (Box 86)
      - 608 Miscellaneous Manuscripts
        (Untitled; some incomplete)
        - Early Handwritten Manuscripts, 19th century (Box 86, Folder 1)
        - Later Typescripts, 20th century (Box 86, Folder 2)
      - 609 Miscellaneous Manuscripts by Others
        - A-Z (Box 86)